Guide to the Norman Shumway Project Videorecordings
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Norman Shumway project videorecordings
circa 1960-1996
1985-1996
V0222
Stanford University
16 Linear feet
Videorecordings (beta source tapes with some VHS window dubs) that were created and/or compiled to be used for a film on Norman E. Shumway; included are interviews, medical procedures, television appearances, films, and other sources. In addition to Shumway, persons represented in the tapes include Bruce A. Reitz, Keith Reemtsma, Eugene Dong, Fred Cross, F. John Lewis, Adrian Kantrowitz, Herb Warden, Sara Shumway, C. Walton Lillehei, Roy Cohn, Vaughn A. Starnes, and Richard Lower. Collection also includes clippings, articles, press releases, and other materials pertaining to people interviewed for the project and to the issues of heart surgery and transplants.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc/university-archives
Administrative Information
Information about Access
Access: use of some tapes may require transfer to a different format.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Noted heart transplant pioneer, Shumway has been surgeon and professor at the Stanford University School of Medicine since 1958.
Description of the Collection
Videorecordings (beta source tapes with some VHS window dubs) that were created and/or compiled to be used for a film on Norman E. Shumway; included are interviews, medical procedures, television appearances, films, and other sources. In addition to Shumway, persons represented in the tapes include Bruce A. Reitz, Keith Reemtsma, Eugene Dong, Fred Cross, F. John Lewis, Adrian Kantrowitz, Herb Warden, Sara Shumway, C. Walton Lillehei, Roy Cohn, Vaughn A. Starnes, and Richard Lower. Collection also includes clippings, articles, press releases, and other materials pertaining to people interviewed for the project and to the issues of heart surgery and transplants.
Access Terms
Cohn, Roy M.; Cross, Frederick.; Dong, Eugene.; Kantrowitz, Adrian.; Lewis, F. John.; Lillehei, C. Walton, 1918-; Löwer, Richard.; Reemtsma, Keith.; Reitz, Bruce A.; Shumway, N. E. (Norman Edward), 1923-2006; Shumway, Sara J.; Starnes, Vaughn A.; Cardiology.; Heart--Surgery.
Collection Contents
- Videos, Accession ARCH-2001-294
  - Kantrowitz, Reel 1, 1994 Jun 9 (Box 1)
  - Li 1 [Lillehei], 1994 May 3 (Box 1)
  - Fred Cross 1, CR 1, Cleveland, 1994 May 4; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 1)
  - Fred Cross 2, CR 2, Cleveland, 1994 May 4; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 1)
  - Kantrowitz, Reel 3, 1994 Jun 9; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 1)
  - Li 4 [Lillehei], 1994 May 3; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 1)
  - Li 6 [Lillehei], University of Minnesota, 1994 May 3; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 1)
  - Fred Cross 3, CR 3, 1994 May 4; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 1)
  - Kantrowitz, Reel 2, 1994 Jun 9; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 1)
  - Li 2 [Lillehei], 1994 May 3; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 1)
  - Li 3 [Lillehei], 1994 May 3; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 1)
  - Li 5 [Lillehei], University of Minnesota, 1994 May 3; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 1)
  - Lower [Richard] B-Roll, Tape 4, 1992 Nov 10; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 2)
  - Denton Cooley, Reel 1, 1994 May 26; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 2)
  - Denton Cooley, Reel 2, 1994 May 26; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 2)
  - Herb Warden, Reel 3, 1994 May 24; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 2)
  - Herb Warden, Reel 4, 1994 May 24; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 2)
  - Michael DeBakey, Reel 1, 1994 May 25; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 2)
  - Lower [Richard], Tape 1, (faulty part way), 1992 Nov 10; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 2)
  - Herb Warden, Reel 1, 1994 May 24; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 2)
  - Herb Warden, Reel 2, 1994 May 24; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 2)
  - Lower [Richard], Tape 2, 1992 Nov 10; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 2)
  - Lower [Richard], Tape 3, 1992 Nov 10; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 2)
  - Michael DeBakey, Reel 2, 1994 May 25; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 2)
  - Dr. Griepp, Reel 1, 1993 Jan 5; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 3)
  - Dr. Griepp Reel 2, 1993 Jan 5; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 3)
  - Interview, Dr. Chase, Tape 1, 1992 Dec 17; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 3)
  - Jack Copeland, Reel 1c, 1992 Dec 10; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 3)
  - Jack Copeland, Reel 2c, 1992 Dec 10; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 3)
  - Vaughn Starnes, Reel 2, 1994 May 17; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 3)
  - Dr. Reemstma, tape 1, 1994 Jun 13; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 3)
  - Wallwork Reel 2 plus Reitz continuted, 1994 Jul 26; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 3)
  - Interview, Dr. Chase, Tape 2, 1992 Dec 17; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 3)
  - Vaughn Starnes, Reel 1, 1994 May 17; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 3)
  - Wallwork Reel 1, 1994 Jul 26; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 3)
  - Dr. Reemstma, tape 2, 1994 Jun 13; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 3)
  - Bruce Reitz Tape 2c, 1992 Dec 2; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 4)
  - Shumway and Reitz, Reel 4, 1994 Apr 12; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 4)
  - Stinson, Reel 1, Reitz Part 1, 1994 Jul 26; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 4)
  - Dr. Cohn, tape 2, 1993 Jan 7; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 4)
  - Dr. Roy Cohn, Reel 1, 1994 Jul 21; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 4)
  - Dr. Roy Cohn, Eugene Dong, Reel 2, 1994 Jul 21; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 4)
  - Eugene Dong, Reel 3, 1994 Jul 21; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 4)
  - Shumway and Reitz, Reel 1, 1994 Apr 12; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 4)
  - Bruce Reitz, Tape 1c, 1992 Dec 2; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 4)
  - Dr. Cohn, Tape 1, 1993 Jan 7; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 4)
  - Shumway and Reitz, Reel 3, 1994 Apr 12; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 4)
  - Shumway and Reitz, Reel 2, 1994 Apr 12; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 4)
  - Dr. Billingham, tape 2, 1993 Jan 13; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 5)
  - Dr. Stinson, Dr. Hoffman, Tape 5, 1992 Dec 17; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 5)
  - Interview, Dr. Stinson, Tape 4, 1992 Dec 17; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 5)
  - Lois Takaoka, Tape 1d, 1992 Dec 2; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 5)
  - Mel Bagshaw, Tape 1e, 1992 Dec 2; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 5)
  - Peggy Hartin, Tape 1f, 1992 Dec 2; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 5)
  - Dr. Norman Shumway, Heart Surgeon Interview, tape 2, 1985; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 5)
  - John Lewis, Reel 1, 1992 Feb 7; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 5)
  - Dr. Dorfman, Tape 1, 1993 Jan 12; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 5)
  - Dr. Norman Shumway, Heart Surgeon Interview, tape 1, 1985; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 5)
  - John Lewis "B Roll" Mision Santa Barbara, Reel 3, 1992 Dec 7; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 5)
  - John Lewis, Reel 2, 1992 Dec 7; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 5)
  - IMC #1 B-Roll, 1993 Jan 22; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 6)
  - IMC #1 Original, 1993 Jan 21; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 6)
  - IMC #2- Original, 1993 Jan 21; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 6)
  - IMC #3 Original, 1993 Jan 21; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 6)
  - IMC B Roll, 1992 Oct 30; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 6)
  - Interviews Dr. Norman Shumway, Reel 1, 1994 Jun 2; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 6)
  - Interviews Dr. Norman Shumway, Reel 2, 1994 Jun 2; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 6)
  - Shumway, Reel 3, 1994 Jun 16; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 6)
  - Cronkite Prog., Shumway, Reel 1, 1993 Nov 1; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 6)
  - Shumway, Reel 4, 1994 Jun 16; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 6)
  - Shumway, Reel 5, 1994 Jun 16; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 6)
  - Shumway, Reel 6, 1994 Jun 16; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 6)
  - Patient Interviews: Ramesh Chand Reel 7, 1994 Jul 20; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 7)
  - Patient Interviews: Ramesh Chand, Reel 8, 1994 Jul 20; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 7)
  - Patient Interviews: Shannon Green Reel 5, 1994 Jul 20; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 7)
  - Patient Interviews: Ada Regan, Barrie Regan, Reel 3, 1994 Jul 18; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 7)
  - Patient Interviews: Ada Regan, Barrie Regan, Reel 4, 1994 Jul 18; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 7)
  - Patient Interviews: Elke Braun, Reel 1, 1994 Jul 18; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 7)
  - Patient Interviews: Elke Braun, Barrie Regan, Reel 2, 1994 Jul 18; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 7)
  - Shumway Project, IMC Original, Tape 2, 1996 May 30; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 7)
  - Norman Shumway, The Vision of Perseus, 1993 Feb 2; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 7)
  - Shumway Stories, Vol. 1, duplication master, 1993 Feb 5; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 7)
  - "Patient Interviews: Shannon Green, Ramesh Chand, Reel 6, 1994 Jul 20; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 7)
  - Shumway Project, IMC Original, Tape 1, 1996 May 30; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 7)
  - Shumway Stories vol. 1, edited master, 1993 Jan 28; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 8)
  - Stanford Medical Center, circa 1960; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 8)
  - Interview with Robert Chase, M.D., 1993 Apr 20; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 8)
  - A Stanford Tribute to Dr. Norman E. Shumway, edited master, 1993 Feb 2; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 8)
  - A Stanford Tribute to Dr. Norman E. Shumway, protection master, 1993 Feb 3; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 8)
  - Interview with Dr. Sarah Shumway, Tape 1, 1992 Nov 20; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 8)
  - Interview with Dr. Sarah Shumway, Tape 2, 1992 Nov 20; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam) (Box 8)
- Videos and Project Documentation, Accession ARCH-2005-246
  - Lillehei #1, Window dub tapes 1 and 2, 1994 May 3; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Lillehei #2, Window dub tapes 3 and 4, 1994 May 3; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Lillehei #3, Window dub tapes 5 and 6, 1994 May 3; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Lower #1, Window dub tapes 1 and 2, 1992 Nov 10; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Lower #2, Window dub tapes 3 and 4, 1992 Nov 10; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Hoffman/Stinson: Window dubs Shumway project tapes 4 and 5, 1992 Dec 23; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Chase, Window dup tapes 1 and 2, 1992 Dec 23; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Copeland (Jack), Window dub reel 15, 20, 1992 Dec 15; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Cohn, Window dub tapes 1 and 2, 1993 Jan 7; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Cross, Window dub tapes 1, 3 and 2, 1994 May 4; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Reemstma, Window dub tapes 1 and 2, 1994 Jun 13; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Shumway, Sarah, Window dub tapes 1 and 2, 1992 Nov 25; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 1)
  - Bagshaw/Takaoka, Window dub tapes 1D and 1E, 1992 Dec 3; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  - Billingham/Dorfman, Window dub tapes 1 and 2, 1993 Jan 13; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  - Griepp, Window dub tapes 1 and 2, 1993 Jan 5; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  - Hartin, Peggy, Window dub tape 1F, 1992 Dec 3; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  - Shumway and Reitz, Window dub tape 1 and 2, 1994 Apr 12; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  - Shumway and Reitz, Window dub tape 3 and 4, 1994 Apr 12; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  - Lewis, John, Window dub reel 1F and 2F, 1992 Dec 15; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  - Lewis, John, Window dub reel 3, 1992 Dec 15; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  - Patient interviews: Roy Cohn/E. Dong, window dub tapes 1 and 2, 1994 Jul 21; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  - Patient interviews: E. Dong, window dub tape 3, 1994 Jul 21; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  - Pioneers of Surgery: "Into the Heart" part 2 of 4, WGBH Nova program featuring Shumway, 1988 Sep 13; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  - Pioneers of Surgery: "The Brutal Craft," part 1, and "Into the Heart" part 2, WGBH Nova program featuring Shumway, 1988 Sep; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
  - Heart transplant filmed by Stanford University School of Cardiology (no audio), 1985 Sep 24; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3)
  - Aortic valve replacement, Dr. R. B. Griepp, Stanford University, Undated; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3)
  - "New Hearts" CBS, 1978 Jun 10; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3)
  - Vinger a/d Pols, 1982 Oct 18; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3)
  - Interview outtakes of Dr. Stuart Jameson and Dr. Norman Shumway from "Valley Focus" TV Program, 1983 Aug 4; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3)
  - Tuesday Nightline ABC, 1984 Oct 30; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3)
  - Transplant Dubs/Ch. 5, Undated; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3)
  - AICD Implant window dubs tapes 1 and 2, 1992 Feb 26; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3)
  - Cronkite program Shumway window dub reel 1, 1993 Nov 1; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3)
  - National news heart transplant CBC, Undated; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3)
  - Shumway Project window dubs reels 1 and 2, 1996 May 30; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3)
  - Stanford Medical Center dub from 16mm film with sound, circa 1960; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 3)
  - Warden #1 window dub tapes 1 and 2, 1994 May 24; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4)
  - Warden #2 window dub tapes 3 and 4, 1994 May 24; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4)
  - Shumway Project #1 window dub tapes 1 and 2, 1994 Jun 2; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4)
  - Shumway Project #2 window dub tapes 3 and 4, 1994 Jun 2; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4)
  - Shumway Project #3 window dub tapes 5 and 6, 1994 Jun 16; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4)
  - Lewis #1, window dub reel 1F and 2F, 1992 Dec 15; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4)
  - Lewis #2, window dub reel 3, 1992 Dec 15; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4)
  - Kantrowitz #1, window dub tapes 1 and 2, 1994 Jun 9; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4)
  - Kantrowitz #2, window dub tape 3, 1994 Jun 9; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4)
  - Project Documentation
    - Dr. Warden, archival footage from Dr. Warden, Undated; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4)
    - Shumway Interview 1985, 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 5)
    - Shumway Interviews from 'Hearts and Quarks' by Jane Wagner, Undated; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 5)
    - Shumway converses with Sidney Dress from 'Hearts and Quarks' by Jane Wagner, Undated; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 5)
    - Cross Circulation from Herb Warden, Undated; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 4)
    - Hearts and Quarks by Jane Wagner, 15 minutes, Undated; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 5)
    - Shumway - History of surgery; DeBakey, Cooley, Lillelehei, Undated; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 5)
    - Shumway - History of surgery, Undated; digital audiocassette (Box 5)
    - Norman E. Shumway, M.D., Ph.D., Volume I: clippings, articles, press releases, 1959-1976 (Box 6)
    - Norman E. Shumway, M.D., Ph.D., Volume II: clippings, articles, press releases, 1977-1993 (Box 6)
    - Norman E. Shumway, M.D., Ph.D., Volume III: C.V., Biography, the Earliest Years, Slide show on NES, Scientific Accomplishments, Speeches, On TV and Film, Published Papers (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous [volume] (Box 6)
    - Slides (Box 6)
    - [Notebook on other people]: C. Walton Lillehei, Owen Wangensteen, Women in Medicine (Box 7)
    - [Notebook on other people]: Lawrence Cohen, Eugene Dong, William Frist, Fred Cross, Adrian Kantrowitz, F. John Lewis, Richard Lower, Keith Reemtsma, Bruce Reitz, Vaughn Starnes (Box 7)